Guide to the Montana Commission on Local Government records 1973-1977
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Commission on Local Government records
1973-1977
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 168
Montana Commission on Local Government
8 linear feet of shelf space
These Montana Commission on Local Government records (1973-1977, undated) consist of general, outgoing, and interoffice correspondence; financial records; records from hearings establishing the local government study commissions, and the proposed code of local government law; minutes; news releases; organizational records; subject files; and miscellany.
The 1972 Montana Constitution required the legislature to "...provide procedures requiring each local government unit or combination of units to review its structure and submit one alternative form of government to the qualified electors ... " by 1976. The 1974 legislature accordingly established the nine-member State Commission on Local Government. Harold Gerke chaired the Commission, and George Boulisman was the director until July 1974 when Dale Harris assumed that position. In its three year existence the Commission was required to: make a detailed study of local government structure, powers, services, and finances, and state-local relations; prepare a revised code of local government law; consult and assist local government study commissions; publicize the voter review of local government; and publish reports and make recommendations to the governor and legislature. The legislature concurrently funded community education projects to be carried out by such bodies as the University of Montana's Bureau of Government Research, Montana State University's Cooperative Extension Service, the Montana Chamber of Commerce, and the League of Women Voters of Montana.
One hundred eighty-two city, town, and county local government study commissions, consisting of at least three unpaid members were elected in nonpartisan elections held in November 1974. These commissions conducted reviews of their local governments and drew up proposals for alternative forms of government which were voted on in 1976. The amount of time and effort invested by each commission in this work varied widely.
This collection consists of: general correspondence of the Commission members; outgoing correspondence to local government study commissioners (with accompanying chronological index) and local and state officials; interoffice correspondence; financial records; hearings on finance, the legislation to establish local government study commissions, and the proposed code of local government law; minutes, which include numerous documents produced by the Commission; news releases; organizational records; subject files, including material concerning grants received by the Commission, research on the proposed code on local government, the study of the state assumption of social services, and the voter review of local government process. The latter includes general information concerning the dissemination of information about the process itself to the public, workshops and seminars, the procedures and progress of the process, and files on a large number of the local government study commissions which include correspondence, minutes, news releases, interviews, etc.
Files on local government study commissions containing only a few sheets have been consolidated and arranged in alphabetical order; larger files, such as that of Missoula/Missoula County, have been kept separate and filed after the entire alphabetical run. The record series also contains miscellany which includes the responses to a questionnaire sent to state agencies regarding their provision of services to local governments, a draft of service laws, and disposition charts.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
Photographs, printed materials, artifacts, and sound records have been transferred to the Photograph Archives, Library, Museum and Oral History respectively.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
County government--Montana; Government reorganization--Montana; Local government--Montana; Municipal government--Montana; Public welfare--Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- General Correspondence
  - Commission members: Jim Boyer (re planning and zoning), 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 1)
  - Commission members: George Cole (re publicity), 1974 (Box-folder 1 / 2)
  - Commission members: Carol Ferguson (re pest control, mental health boards, county development councils, etc.), 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 3)
  - Commission members: Harold Gerke, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 4)
  - Commission members: Dale Harris (re administration of the Commission), 1973-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 5)
  - Commission members: Mitch Leveque (re federal financial assistance), 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 6)
  - Commission members: Lauren McKinsey (re public education), 1976 (Box-folder 1 / 7)
  - Commission members: Bruce Midgett (re the arts and libraries), 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 8)
  - Commission members: Beth Richter (re health care), 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 9)
  - Commission members: Mary Rohn (re welfare), 1977 (Box-folder 1 / 10)
  - Commission members: Steve Turkiewicz (re financial matters), 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 11)
  - Commission members: David Wanzenreid (re administration of the Commission), 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 12)
  - Commission members: Opal Winebrenner (re economic and social services), 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 13)
  - Commission members: miscellaneous, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 14)
  - Governor's Office: Attorney General, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 15)
  - Governor's Office: Thomas L. Judge, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 16)
  - Governor's Office: Human Resources Planning and Research Project, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 17)
  - Governor's Office: Lieutenant Governor, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 18)
  - Governor's Office: Office of Budget and Policy Planning, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 19)
  - Legislative Assembly: general, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 20)
  - Legislative Council, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 21)
  - Montana organizations: Institute of the Rockies, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 22)
  - Montana organizations: League of Women Voters, 1974 (Box-folder 1 / 23)
  - Montana organizations: Montana Association of Counties, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 24)
  - Montana organizations: Montana League of Cities and Towns, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 25)
  - Montana organizations: Northern Rockies Action Group, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 26)
  - Montana organizations: miscellaneous, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 27)
  - National organizations: Advisory Council on Intergovernmental Relations, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 28)
  - National organizations: Great Open Spaces City Management Association, 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 29)
  - National organizations: International City Management Association, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 30)
  - National organizations: National Association of Counties, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 31)
  - National organizations: National Municipal League, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 32)
  - National organizations: miscellaneous, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 33)
  - State agencies: Department of Community Affairs, 1976 (Box-folder 1 / 34)
  - State agencies: Department of Community Affairs director Ronald Richards, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 35)
  - State agencies: Department of Community Affairs, Division of Local Government Services, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 36)
  - State agencies: Department of Community Affairs, Division of Planning, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 37)
  - State agencies: (re education), 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 38)
  - State agencies: Department of Health and Environmental Sciences, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 39)
  - State agencies: Department of Justice, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 40)
  - State agencies: Department of Revenue, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 41)
  - State agencies: Department of Social and Rehabilitation Services, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 42)
  - State agencies: Montana Advisory Council on Children and Youth, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 43)
  - State agencies: State-Local Coordinator, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 44)
  - State agencies: miscellaneous, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 45)
  - States, other, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 46)
  - United States Senators, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 47)
  - United States Representatives, 1975 (Box-folder 1 / 48)
  - Universities: Cooperative Extension Service, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 49)
  - Universities: Professor William Crowley, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 50)
  - Universities: Montana State University, Bozeman, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1 / 51)
  - Universities: University of Montana, Missoula, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 52)
  - Universities: University of Montana, Missoula, Bureau of Government Research, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 1 / 53)
- Outgoing Correspondence
  - Index to correspondence of local government study commissioners, 1977 (Box-folder 1 / 54)
  - To local government study commissioners, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 1 / 55-57)
  - To local officials, state and local organizations, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
- Interoffice Correspondence
  - Interoffice correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 2 / 2-4)
- Financial Records
  - Budgets, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 2 / 5)
- Hearings
  - Public hearings on local government finance, Billings, 1975 (Box-folder 2 / 6)
  - Public hearings on local government study commission enabling legislation held in Billings, Glasgow, Great Falls, Helena, Missoula, and Kalispell, 1974-1975, undated (Box-folder 2 / 7)
  - Public hearings on proposed code on local government held in Butte, Great Falls, Billings, Miles City, Wolf Point, Helena, and Missoula, 1976 (Box-folder 2 / 8-10)
- Minutes
  - Minutes, 1974 March - 1976 October (Box-folder 2 / 11-19)
  - Minutes, 1976 October - 1977 April (Box-folder 3 / 1-2)
- Press Releases
  - News releases, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 3)
  - News releases (re public hearings), 1974-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 4)
  - News releases (re voter review process), 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 5)
- Organizational Records
  - Timetables for voter review process, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 6)
  - Membership lists of local government study commissions, 1975, undated (Box-folder 3 / 7)
  - Project outlines, agendas, and progress reports; rules of procedure, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 8)
  - State Commission members and staff: titles, biographical sketches, areas of responsibility, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 9)
- Photographs
  - List of photographs transferred to Photo Archives (Box-folder 3 / 10)
- Printed Material
  - List of printed material transferred to Library (Box-folder 3 / 11)
- Subject Files
  - Contracts: Montana Arts Council, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 12)
  - Contracts: Department of Social and Rehabilitation Services, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 13)
  - Contracts: miscellaneous, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 3 / 14)
  - Governor's Advisory Commission on Local Government, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 15)
  - Grants: Mountain States Regional Medical Program, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 16-20)
  - Grants: U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 21-25)
  - Grants: U.S. Department of Labor, Manpower Administration, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3 / 26)
  - Montana Association of Counties, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 3 / 27-28)
  - Proposed code on local government: citizen groups concerned with local government, 1973-1974, undated (Box-folder 3 / 29)
  - Proposed code on local government: financing local government study commissions, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 4 / 1)
  - Proposed code on local government: organizations' comments on the code, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 4 / 2)
  - Proposed code on local government: services and structures project, 1975, undated (Box-folder 4 / 3-4)
  - Proposed code on local government: staff preparation of the code, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 4 / 5)
  - Proposed code on local government: animal control, 1977, undated (Box-folder 4 / 6)
  - Proposed code on local government: the arts, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 4 / 7)
  - Proposed code on local government: the courts, undated (Box-folder 4 / 8)
  - Proposed code on local government: emergency services, 1976, undated (Box-folder 4 / 9)
  - Proposed code on local government: finance, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 4 / 10-11)
  - Proposed code on local government: libraries, 1976, undated (Box-folder 4 / 12)
  - Proposed code on local government: printing, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 4 / 13)
  - Proposed code on local government: public health, 1976, undated (Box-folder 4 / 14)
  - Proposed code on local government: utilities, 1977, undated (Box-folder 4 / 15)
  - Proposed code on local government: miscellaneous, 1977, undated (Box-folder 4 / 16-17)
  - State assumption of social services, undated (Box-folder 4 / 18-19)
  - State assumption of welfare activities, 1976 (Box-folder 4 / 20)
  - Voter review process: activities of local government study commissions, 1975, undated (Box-folder 4 / 21)
  - Voter review process: alternative forms of local government, general information, 1974-1975, undated (Box-folder 4 / 22)
  - Voter review process: alternative forms of local government, bills, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 4 / 23-24)
  - Voter review process: alternative forms of local government, H.B. 176-180, 1975 (Box-folder 4 / 25)
  - Voter review process: alternative forms of local government, elections, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 4 / 26)
  - Voter review process: alternative forms of local government, service transfers, 1975, undated (Box-folder 5 / 1)
  - Voter review process: alternative forms of local government, tentative decisions by local government study commissions, 1976, undated (Box-folder 5 / 2)
  - Voter review process: background information, 1976, undated (Box-folder 5 / 3)
  - Voter review process: consultants, 1975 (Box-folder 5 / 4)
  - Voter review process: Dawson College workshop on local government review, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 5 / 5)
  - Voter review process: elections of study commissioners, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 5 / 6)
  - Voter review process: financial operations and budgets of the State Commission, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 7)
  - Voter review process: Institute of the Rockies seminars on local government, 1974 (Box-folder 5 / 8)
  - Voter review process: meetings between the State Commission and local commissions, 1975-1976, undated (Box-folder 5 / 9)
  - Voter review process: model final report and certificates establishing existing and proposed plans on government by local government study commissions, undated (Box-folder 5 / 10)
  - Voter review process: Montana State University Institute for Teacher Training in Local Government Review, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 5 / 11)
  - Voter review process: newspaper and magazine articles, 1974-1976, undated (Box-folder 5 / 12)
  - Voter review process: procedures, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 5 / 13)
  - Voter review process: public information, 1973-1974, undated (Box-folder 5 / 14-15)
  - Voter review process: radio and television announcements, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 16)
  - Voter review process: sister city manager program, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 17)
  - Voter review process: slide show, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 5 / 18)
  - Voter review process: speeches, 1975, undated (Box-folder 5 / 19)
  - Voter review process: state funding, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 5 / 20)
  - Voter review process: training of State Commission staff by the Northern Rockies Action Group, 1975-1976, undated (Box-folder 5 / 21)
  - Voter review process: University of Montana Bureau of Government Research programs on local government, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 22-23)
  - Voter review process: workshops and consulting activities of the State Commission, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 24-25)
  - Voter review process: workshops, forums, and activities sponsored by outside organizations, 1975-1976, undated (Box-folder 5 / 26)
  - Voter review process: workshops on city-county form of local government, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 27)
  - Voter review process: workshops on conducting the transition between forms of local government, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 5 / 28)
  - Voter review process: county commissions, B-V, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 29-31)
  - Voter review process: Cascade County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 5 / 32)
  - Voter review process: Custer County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 1)
  - Voter review process: Daniels County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 2)
  - Voter review process: Dawson County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 3)
  - Voter review process: Flathead County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 4)
  - Voter review process: Gallatin County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 5-6)
  - Voter review process: Golden Valley County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 7)
  - Voter review process: Granite County, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 6 / 8)
  - Voter review process: Lewis and Clark County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 9)
  - Voter review process: Lincoln County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 10)
  - Voter review process: Park County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 11)
  - Voter review process: Powell County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 12)
  - Voter review process: Ravalli County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 13)
  - Voter review process: Valley County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 14)
  - Voter review process: Wheatland County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 15)
  - Voter review process: Wibaux County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 16)
  - Voter review process: Yellowstone County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 17-18)
  - Voter review process: cities and towns local commissions, A-W, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 19-21)
  - Voter review process: Anaconda/Deer Lodge County, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 6 / 22-24)
  - Voter review process: Billings, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 7 / 1-3)
  - Voter review process: Bozeman, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 4-5)
  - Voter review process: Butte/Silver Bow County, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 6)
  - Voter review process: Clyde Park, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 7)
  - Voter review process: Deer Lodge, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 8)
  - Voter review process: Dillon, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 9)
  - Voter review process: East Helena, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 10)
  - Voter review process: Glendive, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 11)
  - Voter review process: Great Falls, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 7 / 12)
  - Voter review process: Helena, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 13)
  - Voter review process: Kalispell, 1974-1977 (Box-folder 7 / 14)
  - Voter review process: Lewistown, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 15)
  - Voter review process: Livingston, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 16)
  - Voter review process: Libby, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 17)
  - Voter review process: Manhattan, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 18)
  - Voter review process: Miles City, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 19)
  - Voter review process: Missoula/Missoula County, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 20-23)
  - Voter review process: Polson, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 24-25)
  - Voter review process: Shelby, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 26)
  - Voter review process: West Yellowstone, 1975-1976 (Box-folder 7 / 27)
- Miscellany
  - Thomas Judge's speeches and writings discussing local government, 1969-1975, undated (Box-folder 8 / 1)
  - List of sound recordings transferred to the Archives Sound Recording Collection (Box-folder 8 / 2)
  - Local government code disposition charts, undated (Box-folder 8 / 3)
  - Local government code summary charts, 1976 (Box-folder 8 / 4)
  - Preliminary staff draft of service laws, 1976 (Box-folder 8 / 5-7)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations, undated (Box-folder 8 / 8)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations: responses from Administration, Agriculture, Business Regulation, Institutions, undated (Box-folder 8 / 9)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations: responses from Health and Environmental Sciences, undated (Box-folder 9 / 1)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations: responses from State Lands, Governor's Employment and Training Council, Livestock, undated (Box-folder 9 / 2)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations: responses from Community Affairs, Labor and Industry, undated (Box-folder 9 / 3)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations: responses from Natural Resources and Conservation, Revenue, undated (Box-folder 9 / 4)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations: responses from Military Affairs, Professional and Occupational Licensing, Social and Rehabilitation Services, undated (Box-folder 9 / 5)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations: responses from Consumer Council, Citizen's Advocate Office, Mental Health Advisory Council, Federal/State Coordinator, State Auditor, Superintendent of Public Instruction, Justice, Commissioner of Higher Education, Montana Arts Council, undated (Box-folder 9 / 6)
  - Questionnaire on state-local relations: responses from State Library, Montana Historical Society, Montana Advisory Council for Vocational Education, Montana Bicentennial Administration, Fish and Game, undated (Box-folder 9 / 7)